<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of Sr. Edw. Turnor, Kt., speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty delivered on Monday the seven and twentieth day of July, 1663, at the prorogation of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2164</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12244373</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12244373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of Sr. Edw. Turnor, Kt., speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty delivered on Monday the seven and twentieth day of July, 1663, at the prorogation of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D. Maxwel, for Robert Pawlet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1663]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political oratory --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56867:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <p>THE SPEECH OF S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Edw. Turnor, K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> SPEAKER of the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delivered on Monday the Seven and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of</hi> July, 1663. <hi>at the Prorogation of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>D. Maxwel,</hi> for <hi>Robert Pawlet,</hi> at the ſign of the Bible in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:56867:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56867:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <head>THE SPEECH OF S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. EDW. TURNOR, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of Commons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent MAJESTY.</head>
            <head type="sub">Delivered on Monday the Seven and twentieth day of <hi>July</hi> 1663. at the Prorogation of the PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your moſt Excellent Majeſty.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe of PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, have ſince their laſt Meeting, in many weighty and arduous Affairs, preſented
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56867:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->Your Majeſty with their humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; which with all Thankfulneſs they acknowledge, never wanted a moſt Gracious Reception. Never any Prince did ſo freely commune with his people, and never any people did with more joy and duty commemorate their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p>The laſt Seſsion of Parliament our care was chiefly to ſecure the Being of this Nation under our ancient happy, Monarchical Government. This Seſsion we have endeavored to advance the Peace and Welbeing both of Church and State.</p>
            <p>Material Structures are beſt ſecured by deep Foundations in the Earth, but the Foundations of true Happineſs are from above: We have therefore in the firſt place peruſed the Laws, which do enjoyn the obſervation of the Lords-day, and where we found any defect,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56867:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->either in Rules or Penalties, we have with great Care ſupplied them: Well knowing, That he who doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member on the firſt day of the Week, to obſerve a Chriſtian Saboth, will hazard, before the week comes round, to forget he is a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>We read in the Story of <hi>Lewys</hi> the ninth of <hi>France,</hi> when he took his Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age into the Eaſtern Empire, to aſſiſt the diſtreſſed Chriſtians: The fame of his Holineſs moved the King of <hi>Tartary</hi> to ſend his Embaſſadors to offer him friendſhip, and to acquaint him, he had a deſire to become a Chriſtian: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Lewys</hi> ſent him Preachers, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him in the Chriſtian Religion: But the <hi>Tartarians</hi> obſerving the Lives of the Chriſtians were not anſwerable to their Profeſſion; they returned, with the ſhame of their own ill lives upon them, whoſe Doctrines were ſo famous.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56867:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <p>That which in thoſe days was the Reproach of thoſe Chriſtians, is much more at this day the ſhame of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: We know more, but practiſe leſs then they did: We generally love a Sceptical rather then a Practical Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and are contented to ſpend that time in ſtudy of curious deceiptful No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which ought to be imployed in the practice of known Truths. Too many amongſt us are of the Sect of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> hunting after Novelties and Phantaſms, till variety of Notions makes them mad: Hence do ariſe all thoſe Sects and Schiſms in the Church, which being nurſed up in Pride, refuſe to conform to any Laws, and make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf the Cloak for all their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations: Whereas true Religion is the Band of Society, the ſinews that hold faſt the joynts of the Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: If theſe be broken, the Body muſt be diſmembred; if they be but ſprained, the whole body is in pain, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber made unuſeful.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56867:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <p>At the Opening of this Seſſion, Your <hi>MAJESTY</hi> was moſt graciouſly pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to call upon us to prepare ſome Laws for the prevention of the growth of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; and we have heartily laboured therein, both to prevent the growth of Popery, and all ſorts of Sectaries and Nonconformiſts; But as the rankeſt Corn, and the fulleſt Ears are apteſt to be laid; ſo fares it in this matter, theſe Fruits are not yet ready for the harveſt; But we are confident, by the wiſdome of Your Majeſties Government, and the readineſs of your faithfull Subjects to ſupport it, by the juſt and due Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws, (eſpecially if ſuch perſons be intruſted with the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws; as do love them) theſe perſons will either be perſwaded to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, or forced into a peaceable and orderly Converſation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56867:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <p>To this purpoſe, I am commanded by the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Commons Houſe of PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, humbly in their Name, to beſeech Your Majeſty, That You will be pleaſed to iſſue out Your <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> for the putting thoſe Laws which now are in force, againſt the Popiſh Recuſants, Sectaries, and Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, in effectual Execution.</p>
            <p>I am likewiſe commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Your Majeſty, That You will be pleaſed to iſſue out another <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> for the prevention of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, Debauchery, and Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, which to the high diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Almighty God, the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Your Majeſties Government, and the grief of all good men, is now practiſed amongſt us.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56867:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <p>And for the better ſecuring the Peace of the Nation againſt the United Counſels of all the Diſſenters to our Religion, and eſtabliſhed Diſcipline, we have prepared an Additional Bill for the Ordering the Forces of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, whereby Your Majeſties Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, and their Deputy Lieutenants will be enabled to Train, Diſcipline, and keep together ſuch a Party as will be able to prevent Diſorders, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to check any Inſurrections, till the Great Body of the <hi>Militia</hi> can come in to their aſsiſtance.</p>
            <p>During the late unhappy Wars in this Nation, our Neighbors Eyes were open to ſpie out all advantages of ſpoiling our Trade, and to advance their own; but by the ſeveral good Bills made ready for Your Majeſties Royal Aſſent, we hope we ſhall reſtore and increaſe the flouriſhing Trade of this Nation.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56867:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
            <p>
               <hi>Great SIR,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but one word more, and that is by command from Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties loyal and dutiful Subjects, the Commons of <hi>England:</hi> They have duly conſidered the preſent unſetled condition of this Nation, and the great expence which muſt attend ſuch Diſtractions: And do humbly beſeech Your Majeſty to accept an aid from them, conſiſting of Four entire Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies; Two of which are to be paid by the Firſt of <hi>November</hi> next, and the other Two by the Firſt of <hi>May</hi> next following.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:56867:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Do appoint <hi>Robert Pawlet</hi> to print this Speech, and that no other do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to print the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edw. Turnor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
